Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts at the Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Papers of Walt Whitman, Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia
MSS 3829, 5604
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry Manuscripts prose
University of Virginia Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library University of Virginia P.O. Box 400110 Charlottesville, VA 22904-4110
This catalog was created through a comprehensive examination of original manuscripts held at The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.
Restrictions:
None
Alternative Format:
Original documents held in The Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia
Scope and Content
The Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature in the Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library at the University of Virginia holds one of the world's most extensive and varied collections of documents related to Walt Whitman, including drafts of poetry and prose, notes, letters, printed versions of Whitman compositions (many with holograph annotations by the author), photographs, prints, legal documents, a map, and pieces written about Whitman by others. This catalog includes item-level description of poetry and prose items.
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892—Manuscripts; Poets, American—19th century
Item List
- A Carol of Harvest, for 1867, uva.00129; xxx.00225; #3829; poetry handwritten 29 leaves 19.5 x 12.5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  The poem A Carol of Harvest for 1867 was published first in The Galaxy, September 1867, and reprinted one month later in Tinsely's Magazine (London). A revised version of the poem was added to Passage to India (1871). The 1881–82 edition of Leaves of Grass includes a further revised version entitled The Return of the Heroes. These manuscript pages were likely revised prior to the poem's first publication.
- Death's Valley, about 1889; uva.00073; xxx.00378; #3829-w; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 35.5 x 21.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Whitman's correspondence indicates that the poem was written and sold to Harper's New Monthly Magazine in 1889, although it did not appear there until April 1892, after the poet's death. Whitman originally included the poem in his 1891 manuscript for the Good-Bye My Fancy annex to Leaves of Grass (1891–92), and Traubel grouped it in the cluster Old Age Echoes, which he added to Leaves of Grass in 1897. The Harper's printing included an engraving, The Valley of the Shadow of Death, by American painter George Inness, which appeared facing the poem. On the verso appear the notes "Death's Valley" (twice) and "Magazine/ April, 1892" in, possibly, Whitman executor Horace Traubel's hand.
- Hast never come to thee an hour, about 1881; uva.00058; xxx.00166; #3829; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 14 x 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 41)
  This manuscript contains two drafts of the poem Hast Never Come to Thee an Hour, the first draft having been deleted with two horizontal and two diagonal pencil lines. The partly erased word "Interp[ellation?]" appears in the lower left corner. After further revision the poem appeared for the first time in the 1881 Leaves of Grass, in the cluster By the Roadside. Since the poetry manuscript has been pasted onto a piece of cardboard, the verso is not visible.
- Inscription, between 1855 and 1867; uva.00060; xxx.00024; xxx.00353; xxx.00221; #3829; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 19.5 x 12.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 46)
  This manuscript entitled Inscription appears to be a revision of other Inscriptions Whitman gathered in a notebook, along with prose drafts for a never-finished introduction to Leaves of Grass, and attached to his copy of the 1855 paper-bound edition. (The entire collection of draft "inscription" and introductory material is currently housed at the New York Public Library.) In the 1867 Leaves of Grass Whitman culled material from this poem and the other Inscription poems to create an italicized Inscription that he placed before Starting from Paumanok at the beginning of the book; in that edition he also transferred part of verse 2 to As I Sat Alone by Blue Ontario's Shore (later the line was dropped and the title was revised to By Blue Ontario's Shore). From 1872 onward, this poem, revised and retitled One's-Self I Sing, was printed as the first of several poems in the Inscriptions cluster that opened the book. In the 1888 November Boughs, however, Whitman reprinted the 1867 version as Small the Theme of my Chant. Note: This manuscript draft may have been written before the Civil War, since it does not include the 1867 line "My Days I sing, and the Lands—with interstice I knew / of hapless War."
- Memoranda of a Year, between 1863 and 1875; uva.00095; xxx.00524; xxx.00993; prose 2 handwritten (Box 1, Folder 57)
  On one side of these leaves is a fragmentary set of notes concerning Whitman's belief that the system whereby U.S. military officers are chosen should be reformed to reflect the nation's democratic spirit. This is an idea that Whitman introduced, although briefly, as early as the 1855 preface to Leaves of Grass, though the present manuscript is most likely related to one or more of Whitman's later, more extended expressions on this topic. The most likely possibility is that these notes represent draft material for the 21 October 1863 letter that Whitman sent to James Redpath, pitching a book idea for his newly established publishing house. On the reverse of the second leaf is a title page mock-up for the proposed book, Memoranda of a Year ( 1863 ). Unable to get a publisher for his book at that time, Whitman waited for over a decade to publish Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ), in which appears a short essay on the topic of military reform, A New Army Organization Fit for America Needed. Subsequently shortened to a single paragraph when republished in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–8 3), it was given the slightly altered title A New Army Organization Fit for America. The present manuscript may also represent draft material that eventuated in a note on the topic that Whitman added to Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ) when he created that book-length essay from several earlier pieces.
- My picture gallery, between 1850 and 1880; uva.00061; xxx.00259; #3829; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 10 x 15.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 58)
  Originally titled Pictures, this manuscript is a revision of the first four verses of a draft poem by that name, inscribed by Whitman in a twenty-nine page notebook before the first edition of Leaves of Grass appeared in 1855. The notes "? for children" and "extend this?" appear in the upper left corner. The final verse appears in the upper right corner. After further revision Whitman published these verses in the October 30, 1880 issue of The American under the title My Picture-Gallery, after which he placed it in the new cluster Autumn Rivulets in the 1881 edition.
- Song of the Redwood Tree, about 1873; uva.00064; xxx.00118; xxx.00030; xxx.00141; xxx.00492; xxx.00596; #3829; poetry handwritten 20 leaves 11 x 12.5 cm to 22.5 x 17.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 90)
  This manuscript contains a rough draft of the poem Song of the Redwood-Tree written, according to a note intialed by Whitman, during October and November 1873 prior to its first publication in the February 1874 issue of Harper's Magazine. In 1876 the poem was published in the group Centennial Songs and annexed to Two Rivulets. The poem appears ungrouped again in Leaves of Grass (1881). Several leaves contain deleted and undeleted titles or variant verse references to other published poems: Eidólons, Waves in the Vessel's Wake, "(a sonnet)" written "for Century Verses," which appears from a Library of Congress manuscript to have been a working title of the group that became Centennial Verses and A California song.
- Song of the Redwood Tree, about 1873; uva.00067; xxx.00118; #3829; poetry handwritten 11 leaves (Box 1, Folder 91)
  Written on miscellaneous sheets of paper, including scraps of prose notes and letters, this manuscript contains eleven numbered leaves. Some pieces which were pasted together have been lifted and photographed separately to show lines obscured by the pasted-on scraps. This manuscript contains a rough draft of the poem Song of the Redwood-Tree written, according to a note intialed by Whitman, during October and November 1873 prior to its first publication in the February 1874 issue of Harper's Magazine. In 1876 the poem was published in the group Centennial Songs and annexed to Two Rivulets. The poem appears ungrouped again in Leaves of Grass (1881). The similarities between this manuscript draft and the Harper's edition of the poem seem to indicate that Whitman revised these pages in preparation for the first publication.
- Songs of Departure, about 1881; uva.00069; xxx.00292; #3829; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 12 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 92)
  This manuscript appears to have been a trial cover leaf for the cluster Songs of Parting, new to the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman struck out the words "A few" above the current title, but left undeleted four other possibilities at the top of the leaf: Songs of Departure/ Departing,/ Termination/ Completion.
- Three Verses, 1860s or 1870s; uva.00071; xxx.00710; #3829; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 22.5 x 13.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 6)
  This manuscript seems to comprise notes and draft lines for two poems: [One?] Song—Come Philander and Three verses. The poems were apparently never further developed and were never published. The leaf has been folded in half, and the verso contains two independent texts. One is a list of names and addresses including family members, friends, and supporters. The other seems to be notes for a newspaper announcement, beginning "Walt Whitman, after an absence of almost three years, appeared again on Pennsylvania Avenue this forenoon." Based on this date it can be speculated that the notes were written late in 1875 (a possibility corroborated by the list of names), but the poem(s) may have been inscribed in the late 1860s or earlier.
- Embers of Ending Day, between 1880 and 1888; uva.00051; xxx.00349; #3829; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 9.5 cm x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder 31)
  The manuscript appears to be a draft of a title or titles. The lines on the manuscript—"Embers of Ending Day," "Embers of day-fires mouldering"—are echoed in the partial line "the embers left from earlier fires" in the poem Continuities, which was published in the New York Herald on March 20, 1888 and included in the Sands at Seventy annex to later printings of Leaves of Grass. On the verso is a note, dated December 28, 1880, confirming a request for a set of Whitmans's books: "Dear Sir, I shall be glad to supply you with a set (Two Volumes) of my books—There is only one kind of binding—Walt Whitman."
- A Thought of Columbus, 1891; uva.00070; xxx.00600; #3829; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 12.5 cm x 25 cm (Box 2, Folder 5)
  A draft of A Thought of Columbus, a poem first published on July 16, 1892, in Once a Week, accompanied by Horace Traubel's account of its composition, called "Walt Whitman's Last Poem." This manuscript is a draft of only the first six lines and is dated 1891.
- [Of All themes and of each], about 1876; uva.00081; xxx.00782; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 19.5 cm x 8.5 cm and 5.5 cm x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 63)
  The manuscript contains heavily revised draft lines written in pencil beginning "Of all themes and of each." The relationship between the draft lines and Whitman's published verse is unknown.
- They do not seem to me, about 1860; uva.00110; xxx.00411; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 13 cm x 11.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 4)
  This manuscript is a draft of lines that were published in Chants Democratic, number 13, in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. That poem was later revised and published as Laws for Creations; however, the lines on this manuscript are a draft of the section of the poem that was deleted after the 1860 publication.
- The Whale-boat, late 1850s; uva.00117; xxx.00048; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 cm x 12 cm (Box 2, Folder 23)
  This manuscript contains notes about whales that mirror a passage about whales published in Song of Myself. A direct relationship between this manuscript and Whitman's published work is unknown, although a possible relationship also exists with drafts of the poem The Sleepers in which Whitman was working with the idea of a whale being harpooned. These notes may be a continuation of notes written on two separate scraps and held at Duke University (The Trent Collection of Walt Whitman Manuscripts, Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library), "The Whale," MS 4to 88.
- [A cluster of poems], about 1859; uva.00086; xxx.00119; xxx.00526; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 19.5 x 15.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 19)
  These notes for a cluster of poems that Whitman characterizes as being "in the same way as Calamus Leaves expressing the idea and sentiment of Happiness... " appear on the verso of a page of prose notes for a poem or essay to be titled Living Pictures or America. These notes mirror thoughts and expressions contained in the 1855 Preface. The manuscript lists various occupations and includes the phrase "not one jot less than," factors that suggest a connection to the poem eventually titled Song for Occupations, which appeared for the first time as an untitled poem in the 1855 edition. Whitman's use of the old long "s" in the word "less" indicates that the leaf was inscribed quite early in his poetic career. Whitman's use of the title Calamus Leaves on the opposite side, as in some very similar notes currently housed at Duke University, point toward the 1860 cluster Enfans d'Adam and dates the notes to some point in the late spring of 1859.
- After the Supper and Talk, about 1885; uva.00082; xxx.00376; xxx.00115; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 25 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
  A draft of After the Supper and Talk. This poem was rejected by Harper's in 1885 but published in Lippincott's Magazine in November 1887, after which it eventually became the final poem in the "First Annex" titled Sands at Seventy. To the verso are pasted sections 16 and 18-19 of Poem of Joys (final title: A Song of Joys) clipped either from the independent book Passage to India (1871) or from the Passage to India supplement to Leaves of Grass.
- The dalliance of the eagles, about 1880; uva.00092; xxx.00155; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 12 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 23)
  The poem was first published in the November 1880 issue of Cope's Tobacco Plant and became one of the new poems in the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass, where it appeared in the cluster By the Roadside. At some point this leaf was pasted to a cardboard print of a photograph of Whitman stamped "Thomas C. Watkins" on the verso, but almost identical to one attributed by Henry Scholey Saunders, author of 100 Walt Whitman Photographs, to the studio of Frederick Gutekunst in Philadelphia, and reproduced in the 1889 pocket edition of Leaves of Grass.
- To a Literat, 1857-1859; uva.00114; xxx.00411; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 10)
  The first two verses, taken more or less directly from a prose manuscript, [Of Biography], have no revisions, but the remaining three verses represent a significant expansion of the themes in the prose notes and are extensively revised. These verses, which precede [Walt Whitman's law] in the composition process, correspond, like [Of Biography], to section 13 of the 1860 version of the poem Chants Democratic and Native American which was revised and permanently retitled Laws for Creations in 1872.
- [Walt Whitman's law], 1857-1859; uva.00115; xxx.00411; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 20)
  This leaf bears the deleted title To an artist, literat, &c. The first line "Come, I have now to tell you" revises and expands on another manuscript To a Literat. These lines were eventually revised to form section 13 of the 1860 version of the poem Chants Democratic which was revised and permanently retitled Laws for Creations in 1872.
- [Hark! some wild trumpeter], about 1872; uva.00098; xxx.00272; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 9 leaves 25 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 59)
  The Mystic Trumpeter was first published in the February 1872 issue of The Kansas Magazine, after which Whitman published it in the 1872 book As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free, in the 1876 Two Rivulets, and in the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass. There and in later editions the poem was included in From Noon to Starry Night. Other drafts of the poem are housed in the Charles E. Feinberg Collection at the Library of Congress, the Trent Memorial Collection at Duke University, and the T.E. Hanley Collection at the University of Texas.
- Poem of Fables, 1850s; uva.00103; xxx.00159; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 20 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 76)
  Two sets of deleted verses constitute adaptations of lines from Whitman's pre-1855 unpublished notebook Pictures "Now this is the fable of the mirror" and "And Now this is the fable of a beautiful statue." Two other deleted potential fables ideas also appear: "The trained runner" and "The five old men." At the foot of the leaf appears the note "last piece (still another Death Song— Death Song with prophecies." All of the sections are demarcated with horizontal lines. Based on Whitman's use of the tax blank, the manuscript appears to be a set of notes he made between 1857 and 1859 while preparing the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. The Poem of Fables as such never materialized, but a poem simply titled "Fables" was incorporated into the second section of the poem Passage to India, first published in 1871. Whitman's Pictures were not published in their entirety until 1925. Whitman uses the phrase "well-train'd runner" in The Runner, a poem which first appeared in Leaves of Grass in 1867.
- [But outset and sure], about 1891; uva.00106; xxx.00380; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 17.5 x 21.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 85)
  This manuscript contains trial verses for the poem Sail Out for Good, Eidólon Yacht!, first published in the March 1891 issue of Lippincott's Magazine in a group titled Old-Age Echoes. The top part of this manuscript has been cut away, leaving the emendations to what would become line 5 of the poem only partly visible. Whitman grouped Sail Out for Good, Eidólon Yacht! in his "Second Annex," titled Good-Bye My Fancy, to the 1891 edition of Leaves of Grass. The pencil note "Sail Out for good, Eidólon Yacht / Good Bye My Fancy / Page 7" appears in the lower left corner, below two new drafts of the ending lines.
- [Time always without break], 1887; uva.00118; xxx.00113; #3839-j; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 28 x 21.5 cm (Box 2, Folder 7)
  This manuscript contains two lines from Whitman's poem Song of the Answerer. This fair copy was evidently made for an admirer: it includes Whitman's autograph in large letters above the lines "Camden New Jersey / March 14 1887—." The lines from the poem are quoted without revision from the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass, followed by the citation "(L of Grass—p 137)," which refers to the 1881 system of pagination. These lines come from the first verse paragraph of section 2 of the poem. This section began as the independent composition 19—Poem of The Singers, and of The Words of Poems in 1856, after which it underwent various changes in content, title, and position until being joined with Now List to My Morning Romanza in 1881.
- [Lo, where arise three peerless stars], 1886; uva.00112; xxx.00267; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 25 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 55)
  This manuscript is a signed fair copy of three verses from numbered section 6 of the 1881 Leaves of Grass version of a poem published under the title Thou Mother with Thy Equal Brood; his note "Leaves of Grass/ page 350," corresponding to the pagination of the 1881 edition, appears beneath the lines. Whitman seems to have prepared this copy for an admirer, with his signature appearing in huge letters above the lines "Camden New Jersey / April 19 1886—."
- [The Time and Lands], about 1872; uva.00113; xxx.00267; #3829-i; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 18.5 x 18.5 cm to 20 x 18 cm (Box 2, Folder 8)
  The first two entries on Leaf 1 appear to contain general notes for a poem; the second entry reads, "Make a demand for the Ideal, (or rather idea of the Ideal of the real)." The lines are followed by the note "in the piece," which leads up to several trial verses eventually incorporated in the second verse paragraph of numbered section 5 of Thou Mother With Thy Equal Brood. The accompanying leaf contains general notes about creating a song or chant to celebrate America and her "best men." A cartoon hand singles out the lines "All the states / East & west, / north & south / Brotherhood / an equal union" which prefigure the whole poem, but particularly such lines as "South, North, West, East, / (To thy immortal breasts, Mother of All, thy every daughter, / son, endear'd alike, forever equal,)" in the same section projected on Leaf 1. The poem Thou Mother With Thy Equal Brood was composed with the title As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free and presented as the Dartmouth commencement poem on June 26, 1872. The poem was first published in a volume of the same name with seven other poems also in 1872.
- Premonition, 1857-1859; uva.00179; xxx.00047; xxx.00066; poetry handwritten 33 leaves (Folder 50-51)
  Thirty-three manuscript leaves numbered consecutively by Whitman in the lower left corner. Premonition was published as the introductory poem to the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass under the title Proto-Leaf. In the 1867 and later editions it appeared directly after the opening poem Inscription as Starting from Paumanok. On the verso of leaf 15 and part of leaf 16 appears a draft of what would become section 11 of Calamus in the 1860 Leaves of Grass.
- Leaves-Droppings, 1857-1859; uva.00180; xxx.00050; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 16 x 10 cm (Folder 50-51)
  After being incorporated as the first main section of Enfans d'Adam in 1860, this poem received its own title, To the Garden, the World in the 1867 Leaves of Grass and retained its position in the Children of Adam group.
- You and I, 1857-1859; uva.00181; xxx.00058; poetry handwritten 3 leaves all leaves 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 84, this poem appeared in the 1860 Leaves of Grass as main section 7 of Enfans d'Adam, and was retitled within the group We Two—How Long We Were Fool'd in 1867.
- [Now the hour has come upon me], 1857-1859; uva.00182; xxx.00061; poetry handwritten 2 leaves leaf 1 18.5 x 16 cm, leaf 2 11 x 16 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This poem, numbered 82 in pencil, became main section 8 of Enfans d'Adam in 1860, and was permanently retitled within the group Native Moments in 1867.
- [Once I passed through a populous] I am the child of Democracy, 1857-1859; uva.00183; xxx.00005; xxx.00047; xxx.00062; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 20 x 16 cm (Folder 50-51)
  The recto verses appearing on this manuscript became the main section 9 of Enfans d'Adam in 1860 and were retitled Once I Pass'd Through a Populous City in 1867. On the verso appear two fragments: an undeleted verse that would be used in Satan's section of Chanting the Square Deific in Sequel to Drum-Taps ( 1865-66 ); and what would become section 23 of Proto-Leaf, which becomes Starting from Paumanok in 1867. The undeleted verse is upside-down relative to the deleted section.